Guide to the Stephen Yenser Papers Relating to James Merrill
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stephen Yenser papers relating to James Merrill
1967-2001
YCAL MSS 581
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.33
(8 boxes) + 1 art
This collection consists of material created and accumlated by Stephen Yenser in the course of researching and editing the literary work of James Merrill. Material primarily includes correspondence between Yenser and Merrill spanning 1967 to 1995 and various drafts of Merrill's writings.
Yenser, Stephen
Merrill, James, 1926-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Stephen Yenser on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Stephen Yenser
Stephen Yenser is an American poet and critic. He is the Distinguished Professor of English and Director of Creative Writing at the University of California, Los Angeles. In addition to publishing several books of poetry, Yenser authored The Consuming Myth: The Work of James Merrill (1987). Yenser has also co-edited a number of Merrill's works, including Collected Poems (2001), Collected Novels and Plays (2002), Collected Prose (2004), The Changing Light at Sandover (2006),and Selected Poems (2008).
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material created and accumlated by Stephen Yenser in the course of researching and editing the literary work of James Merrill. Material primarily includes correspondence between Yenser and Merrill spanning 1967 to 1995 and various drafts of Merrill's writings.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1967-1991. II. Writings and Other Papers, 1970-2001.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Yenser, Stephen; Merrill, James, 1926-1995
- Correspondence, 1967-1991; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. contains letters between Stephen Yenser and James Merrill and letters to Yenser from Peter Hooten.
  - Merrill, James
    - 1967-1971 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - 1972-1973 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - 1974-1978 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
    - 1979-1981 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - 1982-1984 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - 1985-1986 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    - 1987-1995 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
  - Hooten, Peter, 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Writings and Other Papers, 1970-2001; Series II; 2.5; (6 boxes) + 1 art
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Writings by James Merrill, Writings of Others, and Other Papers. Writings by James Merrill are arranged alphabetically by title, with untitled writings filed at the end of the subseries. Writings of Others are arranged alphabetically by author.
  Writings by James Merrill contain mostly typescript drafts of Merrill's writings, many containing manuscript corrections and notes. Also included are proofs, notebooks, and correspondence related to Merrill's works. Writings of Others include the libretto of Phaedra: An Opera in Two Acts, by Bernard de Zogheb, which contains a foreword written by Merrill; as well as photocopies of a poetic tribute to James Merrill, written by Rachel Hadas. Other Papers include a photograph of Merrill and a plate engraved with a swan.
  - Writings by James Merrill
    - The Bait, typescript (photocopy), with letter to Yenser from Washington University Library dated 2001, 2001, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "The Birthday," typescript (photocopy) and manuscript notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Braving the Elements
      - Drafts of poems from the book, newspaper clipping, typescript, and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Proofs (photocopy), circa 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Coda: The Higher Keys, drafts, typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - A Different Person
      - Yanina Notebook #1, circa 1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Drafts, typescript, with corrections, circa 1993 (Box 3, Folder 27-30)
      - Typescript pages, circa 1993 (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
      - Typescript, bound in two volumes, circa 1993 (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
    - Divine Comedies, drafts of poems, including The Book of Ephraim, autograph manuscript, typescript, and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 36-40)
    - The Fire Season, drafts of poems from the book, typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - The Image Maker, draft, typescript and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - The Inner Room, drafts, typescript and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1988 (Box 5, Folder 43-44)
    - Last Poems, correspondence, corrected typescript and typescript (photocopy) drafts, proofs, and printed prospectus, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 45-48)
    - The Late Settings, drafts, typescript and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 49-50)
    - Mirabell's Books of Number, drafts, typescript and typescript (photocopy), with corrections and notes, circa 1978 (Box 6, Folder 51-52)
    - "Rose," typescript (photocopy), 1949?, undated (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - A Scattering of Salts
      - Drafts, typescript and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1995 (Box 7, Folder 54-55)
      - Draft, typescript, circa 1995 (Box 7, Folder 56)
      - Advance uncorrected proof, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 57-58)
    - Scripts for the Pageant, drafts, typescript and typescript (photocopy), with corrections, circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 59-60)
    - Voices from Sandover, shooting script, typescript (photocopy), with corrections, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 61-62)
    - "Yánnina, for Stephen Yenser," typescript drafts, with corrections, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - The Yellow Pages, typescript, circa 1974 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Ouija Board Session, manuscript and typescript, 1976 March 29 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Ouija Board Session, manuscript, 1977 May 22 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Greek child's notebook, containing short verse by Merrill, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Writings of Others
    - de Zogheb, Bernard. Phaedra: an opera in two acts, libretto, with forward by James Merrill, undated (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Hadas, Rachel. "Six Poems for James Merrill," printed version (photocopy), undated (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Other Papers
    - Photograph of James Merrill by Tom Victor, inscribed to Stephen Yenser by Merrill, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Plate with engraving of swan, undated (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - [Wooden stick with a metal point that has a decorative metal casing, with the other end wrapped in rope], undated (Box 9 (Art))